A Guide to the Papers of John Singleton Mosby, ca. [1850]-1916
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Singleton Mosby ca. [1850]-1916
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Various
71 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through gift and purchase, ca. 1930-present.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Singleton Mosby was born outside Richmond, Virginia on December 6, 1833. Mosby lived in Nelson County, Virginia until the age of six when his father moved to adjoining Albemarle County, four miles from Charlottesville and within viewing distance of Thomas Jefferson's Monticello. After showing proficiency in Greek during grade school, he enrolled at the University of Virginia on October 3, 1850. Mosby was expelled from the University after shooting a fellow student, and took up several months of study in a local law office. He soon passed the bar and set up his own practice in nearby Howardsville, also in Albemarle County.
On December 30, 1857 Mosby married Pauline Clarke in Bristol, Virginia. Their first child, a daughter named May, was born on May 10, 1859. When Virginia followed other Southern states and voted to secede from the Union in 1860, Mosby decided to enlist in the Confederate army.
At first Mosby followed a local company of infantry, but quickly transferred to the cavalry corps of Gen. J.E.B. Stuart, and became acquainted with the duties of a scout. Before too long, however, Mosby was eager to form his own command that would not be bound by traditional army rules of engagement. In January 1863, Stuart approved Mosby's plan and gave him a few men to begin his operation. Mosby and his partisan rangers were later incorporated into the regular Confederate army. Their primary objectives consisted of destroying railroad supply lines between Washington and Northern Virginia, as well as intercepting dispatches and horses and capturing Union soldiers. Mosby's numbers rose from one dozen to a few hundred by the end of the war. Mosby's rank likewise rose steadily; his final promotion to colonel came in January 1865. Gen. Robert E. Lee cited Mosby for meritorious service more often than any other Confederate officer during the course of the war.
Mosby retreated into a self-imposed exile after the war until he acquired his parole from General U.S. Grant. He settled down in Warrenton, Virginia to re-establish his law practice. Politics, however, called to him. When Grant became president in 1869, Mosby visited him in the White House and offered his support. Mosby publicly backed the Republican in his 1872 re-election bid, and Grant carried Virginia. Under Hayes, Grant's successor, Mosby became a consul to Hong Kong (1878-1885). After returning to the United States, he became active on the lecture circuit and penned his war reminiscences and several other works for magazines and newspapers, spreading his account of his exploits during the war. After a series of physical debilitations, Mosby died on May 30, 1916 at the age of 82.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 67 items, chiefly letters of Mosby to friends and photographs and portraits of Mosby.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - John S. Mosby to William F. Wickham 1849 July 16, ALS
    Concerning the service of the late Dr. James McClurg as a surgeon in the Revolutionary War.
    #15753
  - John S. Mosby to William F. Wickham 1849 August 6, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Mr. Martin 1858 March 17, ALS
    #10804
  - John S. Mosby, General orders 1863 March 12, ADS
    #38-441
  - John S. Mosby, Farewell Statement to his troops 1865 April 21, ADS
    Contemporary? copy in an unidentified hand.
    #15009
  - John S. Mosby to Stilson Hutchins 1879 June 29, ALS
    #9971
  - John S. Mosby to Mr. Queen ca. 1885?, ALS
    #7036
  - John S. Mosby to John C. Ropes 1897 October 3, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Reuben Page 1902 Jun 11, ALS
    #5220
  - John S. Mosby to William J. McGee 1902 September 28, ALS
    #10640-3
  - John S. Mosby to William J. McGee 1903 December 19, ALS
    #10640-4
  - John S. Mosby to "Dear Gaston" 1904 August 27, ALS #12113
  - John S. Mosby to Colonel Peters 1905 March 20, ALS
    #1001
  - John S. Mosby to R.T.W. Duke 1908 April 17, ALS
    #9521-j
  - John S. Mosby to R.T.W. Duke 1909 November 25, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to R.T.W. Duke 1909 December 1, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Thomas P. Bryan 1909 December 7, TLS (carbon)
    #5415-c
  - John S. Mosby to Col. E. Leroy Sweetser 1910 July 13, ALS
    #5415
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1910 July 28, ALS
  - John S. Mosby from Percy Cross Standing 1910 August 3, TL
    #5415-d
  - John S. Mosby, newsclippings 1910 August 14
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1910 August 31, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke; miscellaneous printed 1910, 1912, n.d., ALS
    #5415-f
  - John S. Mosby to Louise Cocke 1911 January 16, ALS
    #5415-a
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1911 January 27, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1911 April 21, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1911 May 30, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Col. Eben Swift 1911 July 4, ALS
    #9244-a
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1912 March 26, ALS
  - John S. Mosby, newsclippings 1911, 1915
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1912 August 5, ALS #5415-f
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1912 September 8, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke [1912] November 6, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1912 December 17, ALS
    #5415-e
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 19[13?] March 10, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1913 May 8, ALS #5415-f
  - John S. Mosby to Mrs. Lena Noland Haxall 1913 July 8, ALS
    #10067
  - John S. Mosby to Mrs. Lena Noland Haxall 1913 September 11, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1913 November 10, ALS (photostatic copy)
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke [1914] February 7, ALS #5415-f
  - John S. Mosby to Mrs. Lena Noland Haxall 1914 April 21, ALS #10067
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1914 May 13, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1914 June 13, ALS #5415
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1914 September 23, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Edwin Anderson Alderman 1915 Feburary 21, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1915 March 6, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to R.T.W. Duke 1915 April 4, ALS
    #9521-g
  - John S. Mosby to R.T.W. Duke 1915 May 10, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1915 May 15, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Mr. Patton 1915 May 15, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Mrs. Lena Noland Haxall 1915 May 21, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1915 November 28, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Mr. Patton 1916 March 5, ALS; with TL, Patton to Mosby, 1916 March 7.
  - John S. Mosby to Jno. S. Patton 1916 March 10, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke 1916 March 18, ALS #5415-e
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke n.y. June 14, ALS
  - John S. Mosby to Mrs. Lena Noland Haxall [?] October 16, ALS
    #10067-a
  - John S. Mosby to Betty Cocke n.d., ALS
  - John S. Mosby, Autograph n.d.
- Series II: Photographs and Portraits
  - Daguerreotype of John S. Mosby while a student at the University of Virginia ca.1850-1852
    Mosby, wearing a flowered vest, and watch chain, is seated by a cloth covered table. #10571-a
  - Photograph of John S. Mosby ca.1850-1853
    Note on verso, in Mosby's hand: "This picture is a copy of one taken of me while I was a student at the University of Va.--1850-53. Am wearing the Wash. Society badge. Jno. S. Mosby." Not the same as the daguerreotype above.
  - Portrait of John S. Mosby from Harper's Weekly 1865 January 21
  - Photograph of 53rd reunion of Mosby's Raiders 1898
    #9500
  - Photograph of John S. Mosby with two grandsons ca. [1914]
    Left to right: Spottswood Mosby, John Singleton Mosby, Mosby Campbell. Autographed by Mosby. #3261-a
  - Reproduction of portrait of John S. Mosby in Confederate uniform n.d.
    Autographed by Mosby.
  - Reproduction of photograph of John S. Mosby in Confederate uniform n.d.
    Bust. Autographed by Mosby, with a note in his hand: "Copied from a photograph taken in Richmond in January 1865." #5415-b
  - Reproduction of photograph of John S. Mosby in Confederate uniform n.d
    Full length, seated. Autographed by Mosby. #5415-b
  - Reproduction of portrait of John S. Mosby n.d.
    Bust. Autographed by Mosby. #5415-b
  - Portrait of John S. Mosby by Catherine C. Critcher n.d.
    UVa Art Index 40
  - Carte-de-visite photograph of John S. Mosby in his Confederate uniform n.d.
    Signed by Mosby. Also, a photograph of John C. Edmonds, one of Mosby's Rangers, and two newsclippings.
  - Reproduction of photograph of John S. Mosby and Henry Mason Matthews n.d.